this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software this is Nate black for software
engineering radio my guest today is
nikolai par log nikolai is a writer
speaker teacher and consultant covering
topics like project jigsaw java 9j unit
5 clean comments and java in general
nikolai is the author of the forthcoming
book the java module system nikolai
welcome to software engineering radio
thank you very much life in this episode
we're going to cover what's new in java
9 the highlight of Java 9 is the new
module system and I promise that we'll
get to that but first Nikolai you said
that many of the Java 9 features build
on Java 8 so could you please explain
why Java 8 was such a significant
milestone for Java transfer that it
makes sense to go back in time a little
bit and look at the Java release history
so in 2004 Java 5 was released and had
generics and was a big change to the
language big change for the ecosystem
and it really improved coding with Java
a lot so that was 10 years before Java 8
in the meantime in 10 years in between
those two releases not that much happen
Java 6 were mostly small changes and
Java 7 - I'm talking about the language
here there were a P I changes and
improvements of the standard library and
things like that but the language itself
hardly changed and so my 2012/2013 was
like eight nine years coming up to a
decade of basically no change I myself
started coding somewhere in 2006 with
Java and it didn't even notice that Java
is changing at all I just never realized
that there were new major version
virtually releases because nothing ever
happened and I think that was also the
time where I got the feeling that people
think Java is dead and nothing's
happening it just it's going to be a
small town he'll decline from here to
its eventual heat death and then 2014
Java 8 came house
for me there was a
if you can change and I think to
everybody else as well having lambdas
and streams in the language particularly
lambdas make problem with Java funny
game was a new thing to learn a new
thing to study and it brought all of the
Java community much closer to functional
programming not necessarily because it's
now a functional language which it isn't
but you could use some paradigms you
could use some ideas on function
programming and so we start to study
that we start to learn about function
programming and libraries crept up
because of that that was a fun release
and a fun time to work with Java and
learn new stuff let's talk a little bit
more about lambdas could you please
explain what lambdas are sure okay let's
say you have a bunch of numbers in Java
maybe I would say it's a list or the set
or what every other bunch of numbers and
you want to add them up so what would
you do you take the first two numbers
and add them and the third and you add
them into the fourth and until you're
done right so you write that code and
you're done and then somebody comes
along and says now we need to multiply
numbers and then you're right
same code again with the multiplication
and then you realize like I just did the
same thing twice now ated iterated over
the whole list collection whatever took
the first number did something to it
then took the result in the second
number and so forth so most of the code
is the same the only thing that changed
was the operation that I did
I threw two numbers into an operation
additional multiplication and then I got
a kind of result out so why not refactor
that to say like I do the whole loop
thing and you give me the operation that
I want to do so Java programmers have
been doing that a lot before Java 8 and
what we usually do is we take an
interface maybe it would be called
operation I don't know has one method
called to it or operate or compute takes
two numbers to in whatever returns
another number so now you have this
interface and when I call that method I
say compute and I give you the
implementation of the interface that
either ads or multipliers that or
something else and this has been a
pattern that has been around in Java for
for a long time we use an interface with
a single abstract method and at the
place where we call a method that needs
an interface implementation we just
create an animist class like in that
place we don't have to necessarily have
a
mutation lying around we created in that
place we say new interface and then we
implement that method when that's like
half a dozen lines and it's it's a
little weird language feature to create
a class at hoc in the middle of some
other code and it takes it takes
surprisingly many lines for just a small
operation for just a plus and what
lambdas do in Java is they just allow
you to create this interface much much
more succinctly
you just say okay it's a single method
and a single method is basically like a
function you put things in and you get
things out so why not have a much
shorter notation for that so you still
use everything else it's just the same
you still this this interface which is
now called a functional interface
because only has one method and then you
when you provide implementation of that
you don't have to do the whole illumise
class dance with the whole method body
and method signature in there you just
go parenthesis a B arrow a plus B so
that would be a lambda like a very short
version of that whole long class so
prior to Java 8 if you wanted to program
in a functional style where you're
passing functions around you'd have to
create an anonymous class where all you
really wanted to do was create an
anonymous function and the Java 8 lambda
syntax allows you to do that in a really
succinct way yes so for this specific
approach to organizing code to pass in
functions Java 8 change changed a lot of
course because before that the
indirection was was so high in the
effort that you had to put in the
boilerplate that hit put him I was so
high that wasn't really fun programming
that way so you only did it under let's
say just extreme circumstances it was
not something that you did like you
would not would not be the first
solution to the problem because it being
honest it sucks looking at this this
this big block in there big block of
code in the mythical so people didn't do
that as a first approach even though
it's a very good approach it just you
know happens to be very worthy in Java 8
and sorry in Java before Java and so
when Java 8 came out you could do the
same thing easier but this great talk
about Linna stalls where he explains
gates and it says that when something is
faster especially if it's way faster it
means you're not just doing
same thing faster you're going to change
how you use that thing and this is what
Java it actually did it not only made
these specific course sites shorter
which is a small game it taught us that
we can use this approach and we can use
lambdas
much more freely than we would use and
numerous classes before so what I just
described the whole operation it's
called reduce and the new stream API
that came with the lambda with lambdas
makes makes use of that has that
operation already so this kind of API is
would not have been feasible before and
now there are API is building on that
and using lambdas IPS it would not be
fret it would not be usable without
lambdas so it did not only change a
small detail in the language and made a
little bit less worthy it offered us a
new tool to to make new solutions which
are much much more to fund much more fun
to use much more fun to provide in
episode 266 of software engineering
radio we discussed the JVM the java
virtual machine as a language platform
that show talked about compiling
languages other than Java to bytecode
that can execute on the Java Runtime the
JVM so we could think about changes to
the Java language and standard library
as separate from changes to the bytecode
and the runtime which of these things
are changing when new versions of Java
come out so what Java it's actually a
pretty interesting question because to
implement lambdas the JDK team went
through various different options and in
the end they settled on something called
invokedynamic which I think you also
discussed before that was introduced in
Java 7 it's a way to express in bytecode
that we don't know yet what happens
let's see at runtime which is very
Anjali normally we say at compile time
and then it's enshrined into bytecode
which method to call it which parameters
and other kind of stuff that didn't work
for lambdas so that we used invoke
dynamic to basically say look someone we
put this lambda here if I not have run
time what to do with it
this feature already existed in the
bytecode when Javed came out and the JVM
could already handle it so for that
specific change the JVM did not have to
change in any significant way but there
are other improvements in Java 8 which
had to make these changes so usually
when a new Java version came out in the
past was every couple years
all of these things will change you will
get a new bytecode version you would get
new bytecode commands in there that all
bytecode analyzers could not necessarily
work with and would have to be upgraded
to compile I need to be updated to new
language features of course and Senate
libraries may then often make new use of
these new features these things are
separable but I don't think that a big
Java release will only see a change in
one of these usually they saw changed in
all of them but of course you had some
things to just touch on individual
aspects for example formance
improvements but usually just be visible
in JVM of course if you just make a
language change then you don't
necessarily have to change libraries but
since Java came out every couple years
enough changes amass that in the end
every release saw changes in all of
these areas before we discuss the Java
module system let's talk about some of
the other changes you thought were
interesting in the Java 9 release so
there are small language changes in
there as well
the MARTA system itself was like sorry a
language changes you said we're
discussing that later let's just talk
about what kind of Java syntax I can
write now that I couldn't write in Java
8 and there are a few small things for
one if you didn't use Java 8 and you
don't know this but interfaces can have
methods with a method buddy in Java 8
you can create a method with its
implementation and put it in internet
efface it's called a default method it
was there for compatibility reasons to
allow to improve the existing collection
API to do some something with streams
without breaking all implementations
long story short you have methods in
interfaces now but all of these methods
used to be public and part of the API
then people found out with default
methods and interfaces they're not only
good for compatibility they actually you
can actually do some nice things with
these you can extend it interface with a
couple of nice features and some people
started using them not only for
backwards compatibility and with more
use we realized that we sometimes want
to share code between these and so in
Java 8 the only way to share code
between
default methods is to have another
default method which is also public also
part of your API maybe you didn't want
it Java 9 now allows private interface
methods which is just a regular private
method like in any other class it cannot
be overridden by the implemented
implementing class it has to be
implemented and can only be called from
the interface itself but it's a way to
share code between default
you said that the default methods are
good for compatibility could you please
explain how they're good for
compatibility imagine you were
developing the JDK and you were
developing in Java eight a great new
stream API that does awesome things so
stream API basically allows you to have
a bunch of objects and then you use
lambdas to say first from a four person
get the orders and for the orders get
the addresses and then for the dresses
you know map it to is nice string and
then lock it or whatever in Java 7 there
would have been a for loop in Java 80
can use the stream API for such
operations but how do you get to the
stream API would have been great if the
operations are just there or collection
so they decide not to put all the
operations on collection but at least
have on collection like the collection
interface have a method called stream
that returns the stream and they can do
all the shenanigans but as soon as you
as the JDK developer put the method
stream on connection you just broke like
a dozens of high profile libraries out
there who all have their own
implementation of collection and who
don't have that method so they all break
so default methods mean you can have a
new method in the interface that brings
its own body and what if you so you in
this scenario the guy keeping the JDK
right so I am developing a library which
implements the collection interface
uShip collection interface with the new
method and my implementations inherit
that method so now my implementations
also have a stream method even though I
didn't do a thing
I can overwrite your implementation with
something that suits my suits my class
better but I get your implementation for
free without breaking my code so that
was the first idea have this for
compatibility reasons and then we
realized there's some other things that
we could actually do with it for example
on iterator I know how many people
implement iterator so iterate has a
remove method and usually nobody wants
to implement it so we all implement
iterator remove and then throws on
support operation exception and we don't
have to do that anymore
so since Java 8 the remove method on
iterator is a default method that throws
its own unsupported operation exception
so when I implement an interface I can
spare these couple lines of code I as a
JDK developer somebody working on the
java standard library would like to add
a new method to the collection interface
but before default methods became
available in Java 8
this meant that you as a library
developer would not be able to compile
your code anymore because you hadn't
implemented that new method in this case
the stream method on your collection no
that's exactly right so and it's even
worse so not only does it mean my coat
doesn't compile anymore me as the poor
schmuck who's the library pelipper not
only does my code no longer compile
because I don't implement the method
also if you use my library at runtime
you get a nasty error because that not
you you the JDK deferred so the third
person she's using my library and she
sees like oh this implements collection
collection has that new method so she
called stream on my library because you
know collect interface a set method so
then if she uses version that I compiled
against an old Java version which saw my
version come by my implementation of my
library worked fine
she has no inclination why my library
would not be usable with Java 8 and less
treats the docks but nobody reads it
talks so she used it with Java 8 of
course and then she calls that method
and at runtime she gets a nasty error
crashing the whole program because of
course there is no stream implementation
of my specific implementation of the
collection to face where there are a few
more language changes in Java 9 that you
wanted to talk about yeah that to war
again there's small changes but they're
nice to have since Java 7 you have try
with resources where you can say try and
then in parentheses you say this is the
thing that I want to try something with
maybe it's it's a stream or something
it's that it's something that needs to
be closed at some point so instead of me
doing at the end of the try block say I
want to close this and then in the end
of the catch block also close this I
just leave it up to the language I say
try and then in parentheses I you know
use the thing that I want to try
something with and then Java guarantees
that whichever path I take out of this
try block either the regular path or the
exception path somebody will call closed
on that variable and in Java 7
I had to assign that barrier we had to
be an assignment in there there was a
good reason for that was sort of
technical reason so there was a reason
why I had to write try and then
parentheses input stream foo equals
whatever
and I had to make this an assignment for
really no very good reason and in Java 7
order to do that anymore so if I get an
input stream from somewhere else I can
just try foo and then do my trying which
you know cut a little bit of the
boilerplate out of my of my code and the
same is true for the other improvement
diamond operator on anonymous classes
another thing where we had boiler plate
or a boiler plate but let's just say we
had more code that we absolutely had to
when you create a list of string is a
new error list and you can use the ones
of the angle brackets I think which are
empty you have to say string again don't
have to say let's string is a new
ArrayList of string you can just say
list of strings new area list angle
brackets and the compiler is clever
enough to know maybe maybe it's trying
to get an ArrayList of string so I just
you know fill it in there if on the
right hand side you don't just create a
instance yet a regular class but
instance yet in a newest class so which
means you have like open curly brackets
and then do something
create create then you create in that
place in another miss class then you
couldn't use the the angle brackets
because again this this case that's
accurate technical reason for that also
not gonna gotten going to go into that
but that was a good reason not to do
that and I found a way to improve in the
compiler in that regard that he can it
can have more cases there so now in most
cases we don't have to put the type in
there in some very specific cases if you
do enough shenanigans with generics it's
very complicated you have to still put
in the type but usually you don't and
the JDK team estimated that having the
diamond operator in the first place the
regular one cut down like 90% of these
duplicate type declarations and allowing
the diamond operator are numerous
classes in Java 9 cut another 9 percent
points of the 10% that remain so now not
only night one percent of these
duplicate type declarations remain and
they still have to be in there so for
technical reasons they have to be there
because the compiler X otherwise guesses
the type with the JVM doesn't understand
so we have to help them and help it and
put in the exact type that we need so it
was an aesthetic change but it also
reduced
redundant unnecessary code yet definite
yeah it was a so it's a set exchange
exactly to spare in this assignment but
the other problem that it saw was
actually naming which is we all know is
one of the hot problems in computer
science because supposedly you already
have a perfectly fine variable name for
the thing that you have but if you have
to assign it they'll need another
variable name but it's still the same
thing so it's always tough to come with
a name usually you end up with well now
it's just an F for file input stream or
whatever there so if you have already
good name and the really annoying part
it's not only the assignment that it
looks useless it's also what is this new
variables name and it kind of gives you
pause when you write the code and I'll
just use the same variable that you're
fine the big change in Java 9 is the
introduction of modules how do you like
to explain modules to people who know
Java perhaps but are new to the concept
of modules the metaphor I used is the
one that I had in my head all along even
before modules arrived at the scene so
when I think about code I think
everybody does that slightly differently
but what I think about coda basically
have like a huge graph in my head hey
you know whenever let's say I have a
class so I would what does this class do
it usually calls on that classes so in
my head I have like a day this is class
which is like a bubble and then these
other classes which also bubbles and
then their arrows because they're
calling each other right
eff these bubbles and if you into
computer science we call them notes and
any of edges which are the arrows which
are called Java and do you have that for
classes for example but not only for
classes you can go lower you can say
that the same thing for methods because
methods call each other and you can go
the other way as well you don't have to
talk about classes you can go to
packages or if you can talk about jars
the graph also looks different at
compile time at runtime it's not an
exact science but it's I think in the
idea that many have and then I open them
in my head bought the coated or I'd like
how does the code relate how does one
thing call another thing and in this
graph these things have a couple of
properties like every node has a name a
method name a class name a jar name a
package name they have dependencies if
you talk about methods it's more method
calls but you know they they they use
each other so they have these arrows
have dependencies and then not
immediately obvious but also there's
each of these bubble has something that
I need
I wouldn't call another method just for
the fun of it usually it does something
that I need so it's the third property
for your name and
dependency it also has something that I
want to use let's call him API these
three things exist on all these levels
let's just stick to methods classes and
jars for methods and classes the JVM
shares our understanding the JVM says
like yeah it's a class it has a class
name and yeah sure it has an API which
are the public methods yes it is
dependency you can actually scan the
bytecode and look for what other classes
does it relate to so on the level of
classes and also of methods method level
the JVM sees things like we do and this
is good because it means that there's no
friction between the two of us but on
jar level that's not the case anymore
you cannot say this jar depends on that
other jar and only the other jar is
there then I want to launch for example
jars don't have names which for example
when you track down complicated runtime
errors you sometimes you stack trace and
wonder which jars disgust in again but
you don't know it was just loaded from a
jar see for english-speakers maybe it's
easier to see why jars also use this
because it's really just a jar it's just
something that you take something out of
and at runtime you just take all the
cookies out of the jar and leave the jar
back you know I remember on the table
possibly broke the jar itself is just a
container it has no identity and this
makes all kinds of problems that we just
got used to we'd use maven or Gradle or
other tools to provide us all the
dependencies because we don't really
have no other way to find out at runtime
what everything is there and for for a
public API so we don't even have any any
good solution at runtime the JVM comes
lots all the notes all these classes all
of these chars and puts them all into
one big ball of mud whatever think we
had in our mind about one jar use
another jars public API that's all
fiction it's all just bunch of classes
running in the same environment and
everything that's public is fair game
so even if you know a celebrity
developer upset like this package is
internal the JVM doesn't care I can just
call whatever I want so that's the
situation we're in now Java 9 comes out
or what it basically does is takes jars
and says look you know of an identity
you now have something that I understand
for the benefit of our listeners who
aren't Java developers can we describe a
jar as just a zip file that contains
the class files which are the compiled
bytecode of our java classes yeah that's
exactly where this it's it just it's
really just a zip file so whatever you
have jarred you don't know how to get in
just rename it to zip and there you go
there are a few terms floating around
out there for Java modules we have J PMS
the Java platform module system Java
modules and project jigsaw
could you please briefly explain what
are the differences if any when Mark
Wright or back in 2008 said he wanted to
have modules not only him but so we
wanted to have modules he created what's
called Project Excel and Java is
developed in such projects so whenever
you have the JDK teams working on
something new they are career new
project which essentially if the entire
Java code would be in one single
repository which I think it's moving
towards now but it wasn't back then you
would call it just a branch it's just a
feature branch so it was just you know
create a branch of the current version
of Java and then just work on the new
thing in the branch and project jigsaw
at the goal to provide a specification
and an implementation of a module system
that was geared towards the JDK but also
usable my user code power code so that's
project jigsaw and it started I think in
the end of 2008 and then went all the
way 2017 and Mark Brown was very very
helpful and very publicly happy on
Twitter we could finally tick that box
and say like it's done because it took
you years out of him so that's project
jigsaw it produced the Java platform
module system the JP JP ms:i which I
think almost nobody calls that because
it's kind of it's a mouthful and so
usually people just say modules but it
makes sense to occasionally point out
which models we're talking about because
maven knows modules IntelliJ knows
modules or CI knows modules they're
called bundles so at least there's no
conflict there so it occasionally makes
sense to say like now I'm talking about
J PMS module because another thing of
course modulus like object point design
term just not necessarily exactly the
same so it occasionally it makes sense
to say now I'm talking about J PMS
modules but usually people just say
modules and when I talk about the Java
module system they mean most likely mean
that J PMS
because the other module system has
specific names like always jolly for the
programmer what are the benefits of
modules we have something that's called
jar hello class path hell we kind of got
used to it but it means that the JVM
does understand dependencies as
particularly transitive dependencies so
I have to hunt them down manually of
course we build great tools to solve
that for us but still technically the
shortcoming of the JVM so something
could be missing at runtime for example
and you wouldn't find out
until it's too late and then you also at
version conflicts so if you have two
versions of the same library that you
absolutely have to use because you know
transitive dependencies one of your
immediate appearances uses let's say
guava 19 and the other one uses guava 14
and no way can they both run the same
version then yeah that's a problem
spoiler it's still a problem so just if
you listen escape you get their hopes up
now they should still it's a component
of jar hell so we add that that was that
kind of problem then the other part is
that we had non capsulation across jars
so as I said as I said earlier every
public type is fair game free to you
free to be used by everyone
then the JDK itself contains some
security relevant code that not just
everybody should be calling so what they
did is they put in the Security Manager
which you have to activate and then the
Security Manager some critical code
paths and checks whether this access is
allowed the problem with that is that
it's a menu a process you cannot
automatically put in all the places
because if it's in hot loops something
you couldn't make the check every time
so it has to be put into the right
places to not impact performance too
much even then anok don't seem to
suggest that turn security manager on
means like ten to fifteen percent less
performance and still you want to put it
into the right places to not make that
fifty percent maybe but that means it's
a manual process and when Java eight was
delayed due to security problems I think
two or of the five major security
breaches the Java had were exactly
missing security manager calls and the
reason for that is that job JVM itself
could not understand that this code is
not supposed to be called by the user
this
code is only to be caught by other parts
of the JDK so because the separation
that we talked about on the level of
libraries also didn't exist in the JDK
and so through the JDK every call would
be understandable so you have to put in
manual checks is this code call coming
from code that's allowed to make a call
so this manual security was a problem
and then last back then last but not
least now maybe it's least who knows
Java is the monolith you had just one
JVM just one Java Runtime that it's all
or nothing and that was rather big and I
think that meantime everybody got so
much cheaper that I wouldn't think that
it's that strong argument anymore but
with docker images and other veterans
Asian it comes back the idea comes back
maybe have a small runtime like only
have the stuff in there that I need like
why would I lock a runtime around that
has electrons travel 80 megabytes well
half of which is probably swing and AWT
which I never use I'm just having a wet
back-end so why have that in the runtime
all the time why would I why would I
need that so maybe have a runtime that
can be split apart and that was like the
classpath l9 capsulation
the security problem and the rigid Java
runtime I would say there those were the
big problems that were envisioned the
model system could tackle I'd like to
understand how modules in Java 9 address
some of those problems but first let's
talk about at a high level how modules
work there's a one-to-one relationship
between jars and modules
what is this modules name what other
modules does need and what is its API so
in the API parts that that important at
the moment because we'd largely talk to
about dependencies and the JDK itself
got split up into about like a hundred
modules I think like 20 30 for them are
20 30 of them are publicly supported and
standardized platform modules and the
other one are also platform modules but
they're like let's say implementation
details too to oversimplify so we're
mainly using those 20-30 modules what
these modules do as I said they have a
name and they have dependencies
that means a variety of things first of
all it means that when the module system
is in play
it can make sure that all dependencies
are present all transitive dependencies
are present the exchange forces this it
will not let you launch if you say my
library uses user spring and spring
users okay HTTP and I know some of this
also Quabbin maybe and then okay HTTP
missing or guava is missing even though
it's not my direct dependency the JVM
would not let me let me launch because
something something's missing
so it understands the concept of this of
this dependency graph of there are nodes
and if they are gone then something's
not right so it tells me that they're
missing that's so that solves the first
part of the problem where some stuff is
not there when we talk about version
conflicts then we just talked about that
you cannot have two jars they claim to
be the same module if they do you get a
compiler on tomorrow depending on what
it happens so not run time like launch
time I invented this new thing I call it
launch time in the book I write a lot
about it it's not really a java concept
but what i mean is like it technically
it's at runtime but it's at the
beginning of runtime not like an hour
into your program the first time you do
I don't know some you do some back up
some some pickup service that runs as
part of your system the first time you
do is an hour into the project I'm sorry
an hour into the program run and then
you realize something's missing crashes
but at launch time it checks these
things so when when you have guava 14
and 19 on the module path which is like
the class path essentially but for
modules then it will not launch it will
say look if the same thing twice this
doesn't look right but talking about
versions the module system does not have
any notion of versions no idea you can
put in version informations kind of like
meta information into the into the
module descriptor but it just for our
this is for us just for debugging maybe
to keep track of what exactly went into
this application it's nothing that the
motor system activity works with so if
one of those two jars says I'm grammar
40 and I'm guava 19 or actually they
want to say that they can they just say
they just say I
guava and then you have the same thing
twice and then it doesn't work so the
Morrises does not understand version
versions and does not actually help you
with a version conflict thing it just
means you finally at launch time but
there is no solution in there you could
even argue that because of the motor
system complaining a solution like the
head meri if I just put both on there
that doesn't work anymore so you could
even say that one path to solving a
version conflict is now closed if you
use the module path and then another
problem which so if you do we talk about
version conflicts but we also talked
about maybe there was a fork maybe it's
just it's not it's it's a different
module alright one says I'm guava and
one says I'm whatever other whatever
Fork is called so they're not the same
modules but they still contain the same
packages then what you contain is a
split package situation where the module
system says like look each each package
can only be contained in one module
first of all that makes a lot of sense
second of all is used for optimization
we load in classes so this means that
you cannot have guava and it's fork on
the class path sorry on the module path
as long as they contain the same
packages so you get an error then as
well if we have dependencies or
transitive dependencies that are using
different versions conflicting versions
of the same library how can we get past
this problem we talked about take an
application that works in Java right
that's the assumption it works in Java
it no want to make it work on Java 9
there are two steps the first step is
just making it work on Java 9 without
any modules of her own just running our
me regular class path jar ball of
multiplication on top of the JVM which
is now much it'll rise that way actually
not it's not what you asked about but
that's also challenging and it's more or
or or nothing solution that you have to
find there because you cannot just have
run half on Java 9 but assuming you you
you've earlier passed that your
application works in Java 9 now you're
wondering like but don't I have to have
modules don't I have to fix all these
problems no you don't you can just use
the user class path as before and when
you're in a situation again we assume
that your application works in Java 8 on
the class path so it works in you
even if you have version conflicts even
if you have missing dependencies even if
you have all that apparently it works
fine and it will work fine on Java 9
class math as well it is when you start
modularizing it and you can do that step
by step you do not have to do it all at
once when you start modularizing it then
you will encounter situations or utilize
like this the module system does not
support this and my personal opinion is
most of the things that the motor system
doesn't support are kind of things we
got used to but we shouldn't really be
doing because it doesn't sound like a
good way to get a stable application so
it just mean it doesn't mean that the
application is bad and should never run
it just means maybe it's not it's not in
the right place yet to be fully
modularized and that's fine too you can
just go like you can work on this over
the next year - or - or even longer and
at some point you have like maybe 80% of
the application modularize but yeah this
small corner of it it's just you know
misbehaves and you never get under
control then leave it for half a year
year longer until things are sorted out
so if your encounter situation is in a
depending basic and depending on on this
class path behavior no problem keep
using that exact same behavior in Java 9
then what does it look like to use the
module system does it change the way
that people write code is it a change in
tooling what does it look like at the
implementation level to use modules as I
said earlier a module is just a jar with
a module descriptor it's actually then
we call the modular jar it's just a
regular jaw you can even compile for
Java 8 it's all fine you can even run it
on Java 8 then you just have one
additional file in there it's called a
module - info class it's compiled from a
module - info dot Java and this is the
module declaration so it's a module
declaration when instead still job and
it's a descriptor when it's not class
but nevermind if you mix it up so you
have this module declaration module info
Java in your source tree and this if you
have it as soon as you have it there in
the source tree and you compile then the
compiler sees like AHA we're doing we're
doing the module here so it does
although the module thing and it expects
the module things to be in place same at
run time if you have a modular jar so
jar with that model descriptor
and you put it on to the modular path
then the JVM is like aha we're doing a
module here so I want to have all these
other modules in place so what I
basically as a developer I only create
this motion for Java what goes in there
it says module it's the first keyword
but don't worry it's just the keyword in
that file so if you have classes
you shouldn't have classes called lower
lower end modules but if you have
variables called lower end modules a
module don't worry it's a it's only a
keyword in that in that context so you
just go in that file you go module your
module name which has to be a regular
job identifier so the idea that the
recommendation is that your module is
named as your packages are named you use
a domain that is associated with your
project and then you reverse it and then
you maybe have or corner of X dot
whatever or comm dot your company dot
whatever that would usually be the
module name then great braces and then
come to blocks requires and exports
requires are what other montes do I need
and you just list them you say requires
work library blind comm framework bar
you just have a couple of requires close
us there and then come the exports we
didn't really talk about that yet you
export packages you say which packages
are part of my API we can talk about
accessibility later but that's so you
put in the packages that you think this
is what I want to support if you
specifically if your library developer
this is what I stand for this is the
stuff that people can use then that will
support that will help them with and all
your packages that are called internal
or other stuff you really make first of
all the motor system guards these parts
but also you make a statement like this
is not supported API beyond me called
the package internal also you now tell
the JVM don't let people use it and then
there are few advanced features
particularly services do not advance
because there's so much more complicated
but because they're not you don't have
to know them to start using the motor
system that you've brought so in in the
descriptor found there so into the
declaration and then you're done you
close the curly brace and you're done
and basically if I had a world it's like
what for hello word specifically it's
just one line but even for smaller demo
applications is like maybe half a dozen
lines
with a real application might get longer
but if you have like one gigantic jar
and export I so require like two dozen
libraries and export two dozen packages
then maybe the module doesn't provide a
lot of value anyway so I think it it
will be like maybe two dozen lines tops
for 80% of the module set would be out
there and then you're done then you
leave done I all you needed to create
your module to summarize there's no
change to the Java code that I'm writing
necessarily there's this extra small
file called module info Java that
contains a list of all my dependencies
as modules so the modules that I depend
on and then also my exported API has a
list of packages that I'm exporting from
this module so I'm explicitly saying
what my supported API is yes if you're
you condense your your exports your API
you condense it into that file and then
you know you actually have to think
about it and this is also a great way
for having documentation s codes you can
now when you have even when you not
having a library but you have a big
application which has not like two jars
but maybe it doesn't know two dozen or
more couple hundred jars even you have
the problem that you create a jar and
you have a small sub project which has
like a thousand packages and you created
two or three of them for them to be
publicly used and the other ones you
didn't consider them to be the API of
those of the sub-project you just wrote
what Java nine you can put into the
module descriptor you can even if you
want add comments to explain your
rationale and be like ok this also
support API sand you know this other
packages they might look nice but please
don't use them blah blah blah if you
want to open an issue over there so you
can help people you can not only write
down like what is the API you can also
have one place where you can add
information and your line of thought so
when we are in a big project and we're
having a couple couple of dozen modules
and you wrote that module couple years
ago and now I start using it and I start
like I want to use that package before
Java lion I would just use that package
now what if no real incentive not to do
it I don't have a real point in the
development step where like really like
should I really use that package
I usually just do especially
specifically because my ID just tells
like you want how to import that like
yeah sure I want to import that and done
now with and my personal experience is
that in code reviews nobody really looks
at imports clauses there's just so many
of them that nobody really bothers like
going through of them and which which
other charges that come from and what is
supposed to be done their way with a
motive declaration you have one source
file where this is condensed into where
you can like if I start using your old
jar I have to add an export and then a
code review somebody can say or even
during prep programming I think this is
specifically good thing to look at at
court in court reviews like it's are you
sure do you really want to have this
this new export there doesn't make sense
for you so yes that means that we're
going to think much more about public
ApS is this a change in thinking that's
on par with generics or lambdas in terms
of the effect that it has on the way
that people write code would it change
programming as the generics and lambdas
did I think it's plain that no in
day-to-day programming it will show much
less but that doesn't mean that has less
of a long-term effect many of the
decisions that or many many of the
problems that eventually bring down or
slow down projects are not that
my name is classes got to worthy which
lambda fixes right or the problems wrong
compromise are often that development
speed cuts Oslo because everybody was
just doing everything they you know that
that was allowed to be done and so yet
like a big ball of muck where every jar
reference every other jar and you had no
oversight over dependencies and over
api's that's where the term big ball of
mud comes from right and this the module
system is like a constant incentive or
let's say partially incentive or
partially a tool that helps you not to
go down that road to keep in mind that
maybe you don't really want to do that
maybe you don't want to add that
dependency maybe you don't want to add
that export I'm talking about
dependencies I want to add another thing
maybe you should go into read the
building accessibility first you know I
would say it now and maybe I said again
later in the module system you cannot
accidentally use
transitive dependencies anymore so what
is very common is in a regular project
that is separated in a big project where
separate different sub projects I'm
coding on X and X uses Y and Y is that I
can just use that because I compile time
and at runtime zet is always present but
my maven in my poem it doesn't have to
show up so I can actually be in a
situation where I'm using that but I
never never declare that I'm using that
and the Morrises and does not allow that
so I have to have every direct
dependency has to be listed in the
module declaration let's bring that to a
concrete example earlier we talked about
spring having a dependency on okay HTTP
let's say I have a direct dependency on
spring that means I have a transitive
dependency on okay HTTP but declaring
dependency on spring only means that I
can import things from spring I can't
also import things from okay HTTP unless
I also declare a dependency on okay HTTP
I don't get the transitive dependency
yes exactly that's a good thing it means
that my motor descriptor for motive
declaration for my specific module will
say spring and okay HTTP and then I can
have a discussion or a thought whether
that's the way I would actually want to
do that let's say I've specified my
dependencies correctly what does the
module system do to resolve those
dependencies and make it so that my
program will build and launch when we
think about dependency resolution we
might think about what may even to us
like downloading and putting stuff on
class path or in the future maybe a
module path it does put it on the module
path if you're creating a module that
part is not done by the JDK by the JVM
of course or the compiler in either so
you have to have this part of the
resolution way like where my artifacts
and how to I drag them onto the
corresponding paths that has to be done
by some other tools may even crate or
whatever so there's no competition there
at all
the JVM Soren motor system starts
working exactly the spot where the built
will stop working which is either during
compilation or particularly at runtime
let's talk on launched because launching
is a clear case I'm not some application
so I put all my dependencies out on the
module path and Java eight I would say
this is the class path these are all my
jobs on the class path and then run this
isn't that file or maybe I say run this
in this class name or jar and then you
run the main method from that class or
from that jar on Java 9 first of all
John 9 you can do all the same things so
you don't have to have modules if I have
modules on Java 9 then I would put all
of my code and all my dependencies on to
module path and assuming everything is
modularized in a mixed motorizing or
marginalized situation there are some
more things that you you have to do but
everything is motorized in this simple
scenario I put everything onto the
module path and I tell the JVM to launch
that module I don't tell you to launch a
jar or a class I would usually tell to
launch a module so what happens then
the modern system looks into the module
path is the module that you won't launch
there it's there great so then what else
this module depends on some other
modules so it does it looks out there
there as well and then it looks what do
they depend on so it builds this
dependency tree in that case starts with
the tree when it quickly turns to back
edges so let's say it's a dependency
graph it used to be called a module
graph I think the current normal
collection since official Java 9 release
it's called a readability graph so what
emerges and does it checks whether your
configuration that you provided it with
is reliable is everything there do you
not have ambivalences like duplicate
modules or split packages is everything
in order so to speak do you have like it
does it look like you have a good chance
to launch this application not all
things are checked you can have an empty
jar claiming to be guava and that will
be fine you will only find out one time
that they actually no there's no
immutable listing there so it doesn't
take all the things by checks an awful
thing so it provides you with a check
whether your configuration is reliable
which I worded precisely to come up with
this is one of the major benefits
reliable configuration this is a term
you will hear a lot when it's about the
motor system you will get reliable
configuration and also use another
important term readability the model
system builds this graph and whenever a
motor depends or in that case use
requires closest writes when a module
requires another module and both of them
are there when there's in the JVM
launches and the first module reads the
second module that's what's called a
readability graph so in that graph that
I started with earlier that we have in
our minds it's also in the JVM now each
module isn't
and the requires clause between them
turning to readability edges between
these modules so you get this graph this
is the first part of the module systems
work created readability graph from the
from the requires clauses that are
spread through all of your code and
dependencies are transitive dependencies
also no static critical it's circles by
the way so if you're done with that and
you start running the code kicks in the
second part of what the motor system
does for you which is strong
encapsulation I said it a couple of
times already that without the module
system every public class can use every
other public class and also said that
you have to export api's so what exactly
happens there within a module accesses
as it was before so within a module you
can use all other public classes and all
other packages and all the classes in
the same package that are protected or
package invisible so that nothing
changed within the module across module
boundaries for my module to access
immutable list in guava there are three
properties that you know that had to be
fulfilled
or three requirements the first one is
immutable list has to be public which is
already the case now so that's nothing
new the second is the package containing
immutable list must be exported by the
module that contains it so that means
that makes the API public if it is not I
get it accessible inaccessible something
exception so it doesn't work in summary
it doesn't work so it has to be public
it has to be in an exported package and
the third one is I actually have to read
guava which I typically only do if I
actually require koala that's the thing
that prevents me from accidentally using
transitive dependencies I can only
access immutable list if I said I would
require guava so if I ever eat guava
these three requirements public export
package I'd have to read the module he
said all three have to be fulfilled in
order to for the more reason to let me
access the code one of the benefits of
using modules that you mentioned was
encapsulation
how do we gain encapsulation by using
modules
maybe we didn't put the the phrase on it
but we've just discussed it the
accessibility rules these three rules
must be public must be exported must be
in a module that I actually read these
three accessibility rules in
mint straw encapsulation provide us with
strong conservation which means if
everything's in a module
I cannot go past and what the designer
of a module thought would be as public
API first of all I still can would have
come over earth if I have control over
the command line I can use specific
flags to break into code so that there's
less this is always there as a last
resort or usually call them escape
hatches so if things break you can
actually massage a lot of the module
system by using the command line but
leaving that aside it shifts power from
the user library or framework to their
creators not all of it but parts of it
by giving the Creator much more
influence over which parts of the
project's API is used and generally I
think that that's a really good thing
because these others using internals
usually has two consequences one of them
is that I'm using code that is maybe
less tested but surely surely less
support it so it might change maybe two
releases that means application
developers that accidentally depend on
internals are sure to be pun to get
punished with it at some point in the
future and this is this is particularly
worrisome because I've seen like memory
migrating our application to Java 9 I've
seen quite a lot of these using jdh jdk
internal api's and i can tell you like
half of them i could just replace with
support api's was really easy like there
was no good reason to do that it just
took some time and it there was no place
to do it there was always do it in the
first place that could've just started
right in the first try so not only so so
not only do you use internal api's when
you really have that like 1% special
problem that can only be used that way
you also sometimes use internal API is
because it seems more apparent or
because let's be honest it's the first
answer on Stack Overflow so with a JVM
stepping in you cannot do that anymore
so the first effect that you're using
depending on internal API Isis which
spec for application developers goes
away but then there's a second aspect
which is bad for the library developer
so the two examples I like to give us
are unsafe in Jane it for what do they
have in common
both of them well jail force of course a
public and
porter project but it has enough great
integration with ids particularly in ide
starlet wanted to show the user more
information that the api provided with
and i don't know why there was no
extension to the api maybe it was
discussed maybe it was just the quick
fix to do it with reflection but what
essentially happened is ide developers
use reflection to break into jane at for
internals and showed information from
the internal j form from jane for
implementation details to provide users
with with information but to show them
nice green check marks i guess there was
a problem because that meant that j need
for could not change things like some
specific variable names or some class
names or sub package structure without
breaking existing tools out there and
now suddenly is not only the application
developer or in this case the the ide
developer who is in a staff spot now the
project which really didn't do anything
wrong is in a place where they cannot
freely refactor the code because
somebody is using internals and sure
they could be like well it's your own
damn fault I'll do it anyway but you
know you don't want to break downstream
tools and stuff so they don't so that
what that was one of the reasons why
Janet for was not seen of development
anymore and one of the Twitter have
reasons for making the total rewrite
with change 5 so let's just guess like
it was like 40 percent reason for a
total rewrite that's a huge investment
that like these people is this awesome
people they have to work on Jane 5 for
like more than two years and put immense
energy into that 40% of the energy was
because we didn't accept what was
internet what wasn't
and with we I don't mean you and me I
don't want to point fingers at any IDE
developer everybody had their reasons
but the outcome was bad similar things
hold for unsafe Sun miss can save is a
class that does a lot of stuff that is
unsafe for Java developers like direct
memory access and every learn C so
direct memory access sounds like
something archaic to do there's no
reason to do in regular Java programming
but if you do in high-performance travel
libraries for example then there's a
good reason to use that
so this JDK class that's already called
unsafe and it's already in a package
says Sun star pad Sun dot anything
packages never used them there was like
a note up from Sun in the end of the
night he's already everybody knew they
were not supposed to use it because of
the name of the class and the name of
the package and the other hint was it
was really complicated to get an
instance because the constructor was
private so you had to use reflection to
break into the class and make a static
field visible to get an instance of
unsafe so we all they did all the best
they could to hide it and still when
they said for Java 9 unsafe is going to
be inaccessible all hell broke loose
because many people realized how many of
the tools were going to break so to
finish that story the unsafe story it's
still accessible in Java now it would be
phased out slowly but the point is
application developers might be in
trouble when the dipendra implementation
details but also those be providing
those implementation details which we
all have to do all the time can't get
into problems when suddenly dependencies
are so big or so important of these
details that they don't feel free to
change them anymore and this then is a
severe hindrance to further development
and what slow encapsulation does it
gives the developer more more power
although the maintainer of a library off
of code more power to say what is going
to be used and what is not going to be
used and also I think shifts the blame a
little bit more because now it's even
clearer what we were supposed to be used
and what we were not supposed to be used
and that's I hope that using a turn
api's becomes much less common and those
faces of these two problems at first I
thought that the module system only
enforces compile time that I don't use
things that aren't part of an exported
package but you mentioned some examples
where people try to use reflection to
get instances of a class and it sounds
like Mott the module system will also
enforce at runtime that I don't use
reflection to instantiate a class if
it's not supposed to be readable by me
is that correct yes so that different
ways for breaking through your library
right one of them is to use regular
loopholes like for example I come like
let's say there's a package visible
class in some spring library I want to
use it hey maybe it's a final I can just
extend it with the public class that I
put into that
package over there cinco like that for
example or then if that doesn't work I
can still use your friction so they're
like let's just let's just call them
compile-time tricks and run-time tricks
and neither of them work and all of the
accessibility roots are just described
reflection has no special powers and
most super powers anymore
it must adhere to all the same rules so
yes at compile time we get more checks
but maybe more important even at run
time as well for reflection as well it
may seem naively that adding modules or
using the module system would add a lot
of overhead for me and potentially slow
me down but you're saying that there's a
real payoff to being able to develop
code faster because encapsulation makes
a smaller surface area that other people
outside my module are touching and as
long as I don't change things on that
smaller surface area internally I'm free
to make a lot of changes and can move
that much faster without breaking people
down so yeah exactly that's that's the
that's a perfect sales pitch exactly but
sometimes people ask like but does that
mean that everything gets more
complicated in that case or to feel like
that that's that's too much limit too
many limitations and my usually replies
like unless you make every class or
member public you already kind of
valuate capsulation even within your own
projects right so this is just an
extension of the idea it just means that
I'm taking the idea of making some
things not public and projects it onto
the onto the level of jars where this
didn't exist so far so yeah I think what
you just said is absolutely right it
gives us the freedom to declare surfaces
that are smaller particularly across
jars and then Gibbs gives us a strong
incentive to adhere to that rule to that
decision that maintainer made by make it
harder to break to to break into that
API do you think that people will want
to migrate to Java nyan and modules or
do you think that there are things that
will prevent them from migrating all the
way from Java to modules is by large a
two-step process the first one I usually
call migration where you try to get your
Java it's tough to work on Java 9 the
second will usually call modularization
taking your class path based code
in two modules the second part the
second step is very easy to take be
taking small steps the first part isn't
of course like if you want to run on
Java 9 you have to run entirely on Java
9 and there are a couple of things that
can break your application moving to
Java 9 some of them are due to the
module system some of them were just
decisions that were made in the sense of
like hey if we're making problems anyway
maybe we can fix all of the things now
and cause less problems in the future
but most of these changes are not
technically incompatible because the
vast majority were never standardized or
specific and do it in a reasonable with
reasonable effort particularly after
you've updated dependencies do that
first before you even think about Java 9
just update all the dependencies that's
already sufficient work work for most
big applications but you might find out
or you might not find out that you
actually did have problems for with Java
9 if you're using hibernate for for
example or like an old version of spring
or something most of the libraries that
come out now support Java 9 and if you
update to them you might go past some
problems that you have you might fix
them without even realizing it and being
up-to-date as is this worth as a worth
in itself and it also means that you
might skip some Java 9 promise so do
that first before I mean that you could
do that first that would be a fair
approach to Java 9 migration is we're
just going to ignore Java 9 for the next
couple of months we're just going to
update everything one thing we didn't
talk about yet is the new Java release
schedule could you talk about that a
little bit yeah sure we didn't we didn't
do that it yet that's detection quite an
awesome change as I said earlier most
Java releases have a flexion feature but
the crux with that is waiting for that
flexion feature to be done can delay
features that are already ready why not
ship them and so I think was like a year
back when the JDK team slowly asked
around like you know how often could you
stomach a Java release
what about have fixed every two years or
fixed every year or fixed every six
months and the six month thing to me it
sounded like a crazy idea I could not
but that would be very unsolved like
every six months really and that
immediately after Java 9 came out or
maybe even four like in the immediate
vicinity around Java nines released now
the proposal was made yeah let's do that
let's have your Java release every six
and so it sounded like a pipe dream a
couple months back is now actually put
in practice Java 10 is going to come out
in March 2018 and the plan is to have a
fixed release schedule every six months
Java gets released whatever is in there
so the plan is to have as I said earlier
and in this project so interactively
feature branches conceptually work is
being done in those branches and when
the feature is like done or almost done
it gets merged into the mainline as sue
and then three months before new release
is made a release branch is cut from the
main so they have three months of
stabilizing and release and then it gets
out so we only know what goes into you
in from three months before the released
in this concrete case I think the
deadline for Java 10 is December 14th so
whatever goes into Java 10 before
sorry goes into the main line before
December 14th it's going to be shipped
with Java 10 and that means we get new
features faster that means we get more
we have to be more aware of what happens
with Java because up to now it was
fairly easy actually to when Java 9
comes out in a couple of months you just
start googling for Java night because
everybody writes blog posts or books or
podcasts or whatever puts Java 9 to the
title and now it's not that easy anymore
if I want to tell you about what great
feature might show up in the future I
cannot say it's in Java 10 because Java
Tennyson is in three months it's not in
there
but I can't guess it's 11 or 12 so I'll
just say this is project Valhalla this
is project amber I talked about the
project when I block about it so and
other people do the same at conferences
you will only you will talk more about
the projects that are behind that and
then only a couple of months before the
release will people start being aware of
oh yeah this siege has gotten to Java
enough so that means that the community
will has to have to change their way of
learning about new Java release and that
was the second thing I think is third
thing that I want to tell you about the
new release but hey the third thing is I
think it's great if you don't have to
wait that long anymore
for nice new things to play with on one
hand we get a faster release cycle and
more certainty about when the releases
are going to happen but for any
particular feature it may take multiple
releases and we won't know until three
months before the release which of those
features got in exactly the Java the JDK
team will also work on trying to deliver
fee
features more incrementally so up to now
for example lambdas and streams were
both a big feature they went
hand-in-hand and they went into the same
release and maybe in the future I think
with those specific features kind of
hard to cut them apart but maybe in the
future we would see like a small part
for example people are talking about
pattern matching in Java 10 whatever
that exactly means that well how it
relates to Java is not that important
but there's a reasonable path to go in
from what switch does now
to what for pattern matching might do
eventually and that's a small there's a
step sorry this is path of small steps
and we're likely going to see these
small steps being released individually
and one thing I forgot to mention is a
long-term support that's of course
always interesting Java 9 is not a
long-term support release so now that
we're talking about having release every
six month of course Oracle had to change
its support policy because usually used
to say until the next release comes out
plus a couple of months but that won't
work well anymore so what what is done
now is every sixth release meaning every
three years a long term support release
comes out the next one is Java 11 and
you asked me about what could hinder
people started used to have a nine they
could look at this and say like wow Java
nine first of all it's a pain but also
it's not even long-term support let's
wait I wouldn't recommend that it
doesn't get better by waiting for more
changes to come into the language but
Java nine is only supported until Java
10 comes out and Java 10 is only
supported Java 11 comes out and then 11
comes out it's supported for the whole
next three years
I guess plus X plus a couple more months
hopefully so you have a little overlap
between LTS releases but I think that I
hope I hope that we don't end up in a
situation where people only focus on the
LTS releases I really hope that people
try to stay with the current versions so
your recommendation would be if you're
on Java 8 start working towards
compatibility with Java 9 now and in the
worst case scenario you'll catch up
eventually when Java 11 is released yes
absolutely so first of Java 9 the amount
of changes in Java 9 specifically
regarding compatibility as out of the
ordinary for Java and there is no
expectation at all that the next three
and a half years are going to see as
many compatibility problematic changes
as out also incompatibilities because
you know they're not really hard and
comfortability so many of them aren't
but some migration pain from java to
java 9 i think what might maybe be the
most of what java is seen in the past
except ever 5 maybe and will surely not
be reached by any future release in the
next couple of years first of all the
total amount of change over the same
amount of time and it's the same amount
of information over the same amount of
time stays constant we never got to see
more innovation and more changes just
because we see a quicker release cycle
java tennis job I saw a Janice committed
to backwards-compatibility as it was
before
so already now for example I'm
experimenting with Java 10 it just works
no no I des build tools they don't even
know the difference it just works so
Java 9 will be a lot of work to attend
unless they do something very surprising
there's no work at all and I would guess
Java 11 is very little work too so again
yeah I would recommend doing the hard
work earlier rather than later
there's clearly a lot more that we
haven't covered many more details and
nuances to Java 9 that you blog about
and that you wrote about in your book
the Java module system so where can
people go to find that information and
find out more about you and the work
that you do yeah so I actually are doing
a little bit too much for my own good
what's also I started blogging and you
can always go to code FX dot org like
one word koneff x-torq and you will find
my blog whatever else I do you can
always find from there the other thing
that you asked me about was the book of
course so I'm writing the Java module
system with Manning principle writing
will be done by the end of the year and
so I expect the release of the book of
the paper book early next year but
Manning has an early access program and
there's still a bit already available at
the at the as an e-book and already
covers all the basics all the migration
and which I'm just starting out with
advanced features which already got a
couple interesting in there as well so
you can go either you can you know
search for the things you have a module
system in manning or if you wanna URL
you go to tiny dot C C so that's JMS and
you'll be redirected to the mining page
and if you use the code as a radio NP
like one word as a radio NP if you use
that code you get 40% off when you when
you buy that book ya also started doing
I want to start a YouTube channel I
watched people talk on YouTube about
programming and
it and I will do that as well I don't
really have the time right now but I
already put up to two videos one about
Java 9 what about the Java 10 feature
and if I could check it on as well it's
also code FX on the YouTube channels
also called code FX Google for it or
you'll find a link on my home page and
if everything else fails follow me on
twitter where Matney / FX and I promise
you no cat pictures mostly Java okay
great there will be links to all of that
in the show notes
thanks again nikolai par log for being
on software engineering radio thanks
very much mate thanks for having me this
has been a black thanks for listening
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by
out your police software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
se radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening